A Guide to the Virginia War History Commission, 1915-1931
Library of Virginia
- Series X: Scrapbooks, 1915-1923
  - Scrapbook 29, Section XV, Volume 1 - Post War Conditions and Activities, 10 January 1919 - 19 February 1920 (Indexed in Virginia War History in Newspaper Clippings, pp. 401-406) (Box 137)
  - Scrapbook 30, Section XIV - War Letters, Diaries and Incidents, c. July - November 1918 (Indexed in Virginia War Letters, Diaries and Editorials, pp. 1-187) (Box 138)
  - Scrapbook 31, Section XIV - War Letters, Diaries and Incidents, c. December 1918 - February 1919 (Indexed in Virginia War Letters, Diaries and Editorials, pp. 1-187) (Box 139)
  - Scrapbook 32, Section XIV - War Letters, Diaries and Incidents (Indexed in Virginia War Letters, Diaries and Editorials, pp. 1-187) (Box 140)
  - Scrapbook 33, Section XIV - War Letters, Diaries and Incidents (Indexed in Virginia War Letters, Diaries and Editorials, pp. 1-187) (Box 141)
  - Scrapbook 34, Section XIV - War Letters, Diaries and Incidents (Indexed in Virginia War Letters, Diaries and Editorials, pp. 1-187) (Box 142)
  - Scrapbook 35, Section XIV - War Letters, Diaries and Incidents (Indexed in Virginia War Letters, Diaries and Editorials, pp. 1-187) (Box 143)
  - Scrapbook 36, Section XIV - War Letters, Diaries and Incidents (Indexed in Virginia War Letters, Diaries and Editorials, pp. 1-187) (Box 144)
  - Scrapbook 37, Section IX, Volume 4 - Virginia Communities in War Time, 1 January 1916 - 29 June 1918 (Indexed in Virginia War History in Newspaper Clippings, pp. 209-223) (Box 145)
  - Scrapbook 37, Section XI, Volume 2 - Virginia Soldiers and Sailors Overseas, 1 January 1916 - 29 June 1918 (Indexed in Virginia War History in Newspaper Clippings, pp. 312-321) (Box 145)
  - Scrapbook 38, Section IX, Volume 5 - Virginia Communities in War Time, 29 June 1918 - 23 December 1918 (Indexed in Virginia War History in Newspaper Clippings, pp. 224-231) (Box 146)
  - Scrapbook 38, Section XI, Volume 3 - Virginia Soldiers and Sailors Overseas, 29 June 1918 - 23 December 1918 (Indexed in Virginia War History in Newspaper Clippings, pp. 322-340) (Box 146)
  - Scrapbook 39, Section IX, Volume 6 - Virginia Communities in War Time, 23 December 1918 - 31 May 1919 (Indexed in Virginia War History in Newspaper Clippings, pp. 232-239) (Box 147)
  - Scrapbook 39, Section XI, Volume 4 - Virginia Soldiers and Sailors Overseas, 23 December 1918 - 31 May 1919 (Indexed in Virginia War History in Newspaper Clippings, pp. 341-348) (Box 147)
  - Scrapbook 40, Section IX, Volume 7 - Virginia Communities in War Time, 1 June 1919 - 18 December 1919 and Undated Clippings (Indexed in Virginia War History in Newspaper Clippings, pp. 240-244) (Box 148)
  - Scrapbook 40, Section XI, Volume 5 - Virginia Soldiers and Sailors Overseas, 1 June - 18 December 1919 and Undated Clippings (Indexed in Virginia War History in Newspaper Clippings, pp. 349-357) (Box 148)
  - Scrapbook 41 - Missing as of 10 May 2001
  - Scrapbook 42, War Letters, Diaries and Incidents (c. 1918 - 1919) (Indexed in Virginia War Letters, Diaries and Editorials, pp. 1-187) (Box 149)
  - Scrapbook 43 - Missing as of 10 May 2001
  - Scrapbook 44, Section XIV - War Incidents, Civilian (Women's Munition Reserve) (Indexed in Virginia War Letters, Diaries and Editorials, pp. 182-187) - [Scrapbook located in Box 79; filed with Richmond City, Women's Munition Reserve records]
  - Unnumbered, Section IX, Volume 3 - Virginia Communities in War Time, Clippings Contributed by Local Branches (incomplete) (Indexed in Virginia War History in Newspaper Clippings, pp. 193-208) (Box 150)
  - Unnumbered, Section IX, Volume 3 - Virginia Communities in War Time, Clippings Contributed by Local Branches, Fauquier County, Parts I and II (Indexed in Virginia War History in Newspaper Clippings, pp. 195-202) (Box 151)
- Series XI: Office Files, 1917-1927
  The Office Files series is housed in 94 boxes and 4 oversized folders and is arranged into eight (8) subseries. Subseries have been designated for Correspondence, General; Correspondence, Local Branches; Correspondence, Section Editors; Financial Records; Forms; Index Card Files; Miscellaneous Records; and Publications. The most substantial and significant records in this series are the various correspondence files which consist of incoming and outgoing correspondence dated between 1919 and 1927. This series consists primarily of incoming and outgoing correspondence from Virginia War History Commission chairman Arthur Kyle Davis and office manager Ruth Cunningham. This series documents the activities of the Virginia War History Commission between 1919 and 1927 including the formation and collection of records by the local branches and the publication of Commission's books. Although the Virginia War History Commission was not created until January 1919, this series contains financial records of the First and Second Virginia Council of Defense between 1917 and 1919. Correspondence, account books, invoices, receipts, bills, books, manuscripts, newspaper clippings, reports, minutes, forms, questionnaires, index cards and other items are found in this series.
  The Correspondence, General subseries is housed in 14 boxes and 3 oversize folders and is arranged alphabetically by subject or sender. The records in the sub-series Correspondence-General relate to a variety of topics including, the American Historical Association meeting in Richmond, Virginia, on 27-31 December 1924; organization, field agents, problems with office equipment, publications and employees, and day-to-day operation of the War History Commission; National Association of State War History Organizations; Negro Collaborators; and Service Legion.
  Noteworthy correspondents include Arthur Kyle Davis, Ruth K. Cunningham (War History Commission Chief Clerk/Office Manager), H.R. McIlwaine (Virginia State Librarian), and Walter F. Beverly, Arthur W. James, Henry H. Simms, and R.C. Stearnes (all War History Commission Field Agents). The correspondence of Arthur Kyle Davis are arranged chronologically include Davis' appointment as head of War History Commission by Governor Westmoreland Davis (7 January 1919) and Davis' acceptance of the position (9 January 1919), and H.R. McIlwaine's suggestions for the organization and instructions to local branches and section chairman (26 December 1919). Other notable correspondence include a request from John Garland Pollard, professor at the College of William and Mary, requesting information about the Commission (12 January 1923) and Davis's reply in which he provides a frank overview of the Commission's work and problems (30 January 1923), and two letters by Davis to his son, Arthur Kyle Davis, Jr., a Rhodes Scholar at Oxford, relating family news and describing problems with the source volume, Virginians of Distinguished Service (30 January 1923 and 28 February 1923) and a letter to Davis, Jr., now at the University of Virginia, relating family news and discussing the source volume, Virginia War Letters, Diaries and Incidents (21 October 1925). Davis lived in Petersburg and worked in the Commission's Richmond office one day a week. The majority of Davis's correspondence is with Ruth K. Cunningham, War History Commission Chief Clerk/Office Manager, and describes day-to-day operations of the Commission. Noteworthy correspondence from Cunningham to Davis include a description of her difficulties with Commission employee, T.R. Jehne during the Commission's office move (20 January 1924), her illness and recovery (10 June 1924, 20 June 1924, 19 July 1924 and 15 August 1924), and the closing of the Commission's office (29 March 1927).
  Ruth K. Cunningham's letters document her February 1921 trip to southwest Virginia on behalf of the Commission. Virginia State Librarian and Commission member H.R. McIlwaine corresponds with Davis on Commission records and policy including the organization of the Commission's files (20 December 1919) and the creation of newspaper scrapbooks (2 June 1922) and with Charles R. Keiley, Commission Secretary and member, about hiring Field Agents (3 July 1920). Also included with McIlwaine's letters are minutes of the 12 November 1919 Commission meeting. Walter F. Beverly was employed by the Commission as a Field Agent mainly in southwest Virginia between July and September 1920. His records include diary entries for the weeks of 24 July, 31 July, 7 August and 14 August 1920 that describe the organization and work conducted by local branches in Russell, Wise, Scott, Smyth, Tazewell, Dickenson, Washington, Bland, Wythe, Pulaski, Grayson, Carroll, Lee, Giles and New Kent Counties. Additional reports and correspondence documenting the activities of the local branches in the summers of 1920 and 1921 are filed with the records of Field Agents Arthur W. James, Henry H. Simms, and R.C. Stearnes. Stearnes spoke about the Commission's work at "Robert E. Lee's Last Camp Memorial Rally" held at the Buckingham County Court House on 24 July 1920. A broadside of the event is included with his records.
  Additional significant correspondence, filed by subject heading, include the American Historical Association, Hooven Automatic Typewriter Corporation, National Association of State War Organizations, Negro Collaborators, and Service Legion. The American Historical Association held their annual meeting in Richmond, Virginia, on 27-31 December 1924. Correspondence, mainly to and from Arthur Kyle Davis, describe meeting preparation, a copy of the meeting program and Davis' address to the AHA. Correspondence between the Commission and the Hooven Automatic Typewriter Corporation between 1920 and 1927 document the poor performance of the office typewriter and the futile attempts to have it repaired. The National Association of State War History Organizations was founded in September 1919 in Washington, D.C. by representatives of war history commissions and similar organizations from fifteen states. The group maintained an office in Washington to locate, describe, and copy documents in governmental archives relating to war activities. The correspondence document Davis's activities as the Association's vice-president and chairman of the executive committee. Notable records include minutes of the Association's meeting in Cleveland, Ohio, on 29-31 December 1919 (attached to a 26 January 1920 letter to Davis from Albert E. McKinley, Association Secretary), minutes of a special meeting of the Association in Washington on 28 December 1920 (attached to a 19 January 1921 letter to Davis from McKinley), and minutes of meetings in Washington on 6-7 April 1920 and 29-30 April 1921. The National Association of State War History Organizations was inactive between 1922 and 1925 and dissolved in the spring of 1925. The War History Commission made a special attempt to collect records of African-American involvement in the war by designating Negro collaborators and hiring a field agent to encourage black participation in the Commission's program. Correspondence filed under Negro Collaborators document these efforts between 1919 and 1921. Significant correspondence include a letter from Davis to Julia Sully, Section Chair of War Work and Relief Organizations (which included Negro contributions), concerning the hiring of Ora B. Stokes as a Negro filed agent (no date) and numerous correspondence and field reports of Stokes to Sully and Cunningham chronicling her activities during the summer of 1920. Also included are two issues of The Central Call (14 August 1920 and 28 August 1920) a black newspaper published in Cumberland, Virginia. In 1921 Mrs. G.T.W. Kern (Margaret Ethel Kelley Kern) founded the Service Legion, an organization to commemorate civilian service during the war. Records include correspondence, mainly between Kern and Davis, describing the organization, purpose, and activities of the Service Legion. Davis was a member of the Legion's Advisory Committee. Other noteworthy items include Photographs of Commission members Arthur Kyle Davis, Charles R. Keiley, and Lyon G. Tyler as well as unidentified World War I soldiers. Filed under Speakers is a letter from Brigadier General Douglas McArthur to Davis declining an invitation to speak to the Commission (27 December 1920).
  The Correspondence, Local Branches subseries is housed in 11 boxes. Records in the sub-series Correspondence-Local Branches illustrate the activities and the successes and failures/difficulties of the local War History Commission branches. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by locality (counties then cities) with the correspondence arranged alphabetically by reverse chronological order (primarily 1922-1925 and 1919-1921). The majority of the correspondence is between Arthur Kyle Davis and Ruth Cunningham and members of the local branches, many of them women, and documents the organization, collection of records, and problems of the local branches. Sara Lyle Marshall, chairwoman of the Fauquier County branch, describes her successes and failures in her correspondence (especially 23 March 1921). Grayson County records include a postcard of Jack Allen taken in the backyard of Floyd Allen on 20 March 1913, the day of Floyd and Claude Allen's funeral. This material, unrelated to World War I, was submitted by R.E. Cox.
  The Correspondence, Section Editors subseries is housed in 3 boxes and is arranged by the topical outline developed by the War History Commission. The War History Commission created fifteen topical sections covering distinct subjects to be included in the Commission's proposed four volume history of Virginia during the war. Each section had a chairman and associates who assisted writing the historical narrative of their topic. These sections were: I. Virginians of Distinguished Service; II. Pre-War Conditions and Activities; III. Virginia Churches in War-Time; IV. Virginia Schools and Colleges in the War; V. Political Contributions of Virginia; VI. Draft Law and Virginia Organizations; VII. Virginia Camps and Cantonments; VIII. Economic Conditions in War-Time; IX. Local Branches of Virginia Commission; X. Chesapeake Bay Area in War-Time; XI. Virginia Soldiers and Sailors Overseas; XII. The Red Cross in Virginia; XIII. War Work and Relief Organizations; XIV. War Letters, Diaries and Incidents; and XV. Post-War Conditions and Activities. Records in the sub-series Correspondence, Section Editors contain both incoming and outgoing correspondence between the Commission and section chairman. Noteworthy records include correspondence between, Dr. S.C. Mitchell, chair of the Virginia Churches in War Time section, and clergy across Virginia. A photograph of Dr. Mitchell (B177, F8) is also included. Correspondence filed under the Virginia Communities in War Time document the status of the War History Commission's local branches as of December 1922.
  The Financial Records subseries is housed in 8 boxes and is arranged alphabetically by type of record. The financial records sub-series contains bills, receipts, invoices, and ledgers of the Virginia Council of Defense and War History Commission.
  The Forms subseries is housed in 2 boxes and is arranged by the topical outline developed by the War History Commission. These records contain blank examples of various forms used by the commission to document Virginia's contribution to the war effort.
  The Index Cards subseries is housed in 39 index card boxes. The majority of these records are unidentified. However, there are some cards for Virginians killed during the war.
  The Miscellaneous Records subseries is housed in 4 boxes and is arranged alphabetically by topic. Notable records include casualty lists of Virginians killed during the war.
  The Publications subseries is housed in 13 boxes and one oversize folder and is arranged by published an unpublished material. In addition to annotated copies of the Commission's seven source volumes, the publication files contain drafts of histories of the First and Second Virginia Council of Defense and Selective Service and copies of the War History Commission News Letter (1919-1920).
  - Subseries A: Correspondence, General
    - Address Books, 1923 and 1925 (Box 152, Folder 1)
    - Advertising, 1927 (Box 152, Folder 2)
    - Adjutant General of Virginia, 1922-1925 (Box 152, Folder 3)
    - American Historical Association, 1924-1925 (Box 152, Folder 4)
    - American Legion (See Oversize Box 165)
    - Annual Report, 1922 (Box 152, Folder 5)
    - Applications for Employment, 1923 (Box 152, Folder 6)
    - Beverly, Walter F.-Field Agent, 1920 July - September (Box 152, Folder 7)
    - Bills, 1925-1927 (Box 152, Folder 8)
    - Book Reviews, 1925-1927 (Box 152, Folder 9)
    - Book Stores, 1925-1927 (Box 152, Folder 10)
    - Clippings (See Oversize Box 165)
    - Circular Letters, 1919-1922 (Box 152, Folder 11)
    - Circular Letters, 1923-1927 (Box 152, Folder 12)
    - Consular Service, American, 1920-1922 (Box 153, Folder 1)
    - Contributing Members, War History Commission, 1919-1926 (Box 153, Folder 2)
    - Cunningham, Ruth K, 1921 February and 1926 December (Box 153, Folder 3)
    - Davis, Arthur Kyle, 1919 (Box 153, Folder 4)
    - Davis, Arthur Kyle, 1920 (Box 153, Folder 5)
    - Davis, Arthur Kyle, 1921 (Box 153, Folder 6)
    - Davis, Arthur Kyle, 1922 (Box 153, Folder 7)
    - Davis, Arthur Kyle, 1923 (Box 153, Folder 8)
    - Davis, Arthur Kyle, 1924 (Box 153, Folder 9)
    - Davis, Arthur Kyle, 1925 (Box 153, Folder 10)
    - Davis, Arthur Kyle, 1926 (Box 154, Folder 1)
    - Davis, Arthur Kyle, 1927 (Box 154, Folder 2)
    - Davis, Arthur Kyle, Undated and Miscellaneous (Box 154, Folder 3)
    - Editors, General, 1923-1926 (Box 154, Folder 4)
    - 80th Division, 1923-1925 (Box 154, Folder 5)
    - Employees, 1924-1926 (Box 154, Folder 6)
    - Fox, E.L., 1924-1925 (Box 154, Folder 7)
    - Government, U.S., 1920-1924 (Box 154, Folder 8)
    - Government, U.S. - Adjutant General's Office, Blank Discharge Forms (Box 155, Folder 1)
    - Governor's Office, 1919-1927 [See Also Oversize Box 1, Folder 13] (Box 155, Folder 2)
    - Governor's Office - Proclamations, Addresses, etc., 1918-1921 (Box 155, Folder 3)
    - History Commission, Collaborators, partial list of local branches, 1919 (Box 155, Folder 4)
    - History Commission - Chart of Members of Local Branches, ca. 1920 - See Oversize Box 1, Folder 13a
    - History Commission - Copy of Senate Bill 71 (appropriation for Commission, 1919) (Box 155, Folder 5)
    - History Commission - Meeting Invitations, 1919 (Box 155, Folder 6)
    - History Commission - Meeting Invitations, 1920 (Box 155, Folder 7)
    - History Commission - Meeting Invitations, 1921 and 1925 (Box 155, Folder 8)
    - Home Guards, Virginia, 1921-1922 (Box 155, Folder 9)
    - Hooven Automatic Typewriter Corporation, 1920-1927 (Box 155, Folder 10)
    - James, Arthur W. - Field Agent, 1920-1923 (Box 156, Folder 1)
    - Libraries, 1921-1925 (Box 156, Folder 2)
    - Machen, Lewis H., 1922 (Box 156, Folder 3)
    - Malone, Dumas, 1924-1925 (Box 156, Folder 4)
    - McIlwaine, H.R., 1919-1922 (A-G) (Box 156, Folder 5)
    - McIlwaine, H.R., 1919-1922 (H-W) (Box 156, Folder 6)
    - Memorandums, ca. 1920-1921 (Box 156, Folder 7)
    - Memorandums, ca. 1924-1927 (Box 156, Folder 8)
    - Mereness, Newton D., 1920-1925 (Box 157, Folder 1)
    - Military Histories, 1922 (Box 157, Folder 2)
    - Ministers, Pastors and Rabbis - Lists of in Virginia (Box 157, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1919-1922 (Box 157, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1923-1927 (Box 157, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Draft Laws, etc.) (Box 157, Folder 6)
    - National Association of State War History Organizations, 1919-1922 and 1925 (Box 157, Folder 7)
    - National Association of State War History Organizations - Meetings, 1920-1921 (Box 158, Folder 1)
    - Negro Collaborators, 1919-1920 and 1923 (Box 158, Folder 2)
    - Negro Collaborators, 1920-1922 and 1927 (Box 158, Folder 3)
    - Negro Collaborators - A-P, 1919-1921 (Box 158, Folder 4)
    - Negro Collaborators - P-S, 1920 (Box 158, Folder 5)
    - Newspapers, 1920-1922 (Box 158, Folder 6)
    - Newspapers, 1923-1926 (Box 158, Folder 7)
    - Office Equipment, 1919-1927 (Box 159, Folder 1)
    - Ordinance, License Tax, 1921 (Box 159, Folder 2)
    - Other States: Alabama - Indiana (Box 159, Folder 3)
    - Other States: Iowa - Mississippi (Box 159, Folder 4)
    - Other States: Missouri - Oklahoma (Box 159, Folder 5)
    - Other States: Pennsylvania (Box 159, Folder 6)
    - Other States: Rhode Island - West Virginia (Box 159, Folder 7)
    - Photographs (Box 160, Folder 1)
    - Press Releases/Publicity, 1919-1921, 1923-1925, 1927 and no date (See Also Oversize) (Box 160, Folder 2)
    - Printers/Printing, 1920, 1923-1927 (Box 160, Folder 3)
    - Questionnaires, ca. 1922-1923 (See Also Oversize Box 165) (Box 160, Folder 4)
    - Regret, Letters of, 1919 (Box 160, Folder 5)
    - Regret, Letters of, 1920 January - 1920 August (Box 160, Folder 6)
    - Regret, Letters of, 1920 October - 1921 April (Box 160, Folder 7)
    - Reports (See Oversize Box 165)
    - Saunders, J. Roy, 1925 (Box 160, Folder 8)
    - Service Legion, 1921-1923, 1925 (Box 160, Folder 9)
    - Simms, Henry H. - Field Agent, 1920-1921 (Box 160, Folder 10)
    - Soldiers Discharge Records, County Clerk Recordation, 1924-1925 (Box 161, Folder 1)
    - Source Volumes - Orders for Volumes I and II, 1925 (Box 161, Folder 2)
    - Source Volumes - Orders for Volume III, 1925 (Box 161, Folder 3)
    - Source Volumes - Orders and Correspondence for Volume II, 1924-1925 - [See Also Oversize Box, Folder 13b] (Box 161, Folder 4)
    - Source Volumes - Volume II and III (Box 161, Folder 5)
    - Source Volumes - Orders and Correspondence for Volume III, 1924-1925, 1927 (Box 161, Folder 6)
    - Source Volumes - Volume III (Box 161, Folder 7)
    - Source Volumes - Orders and Correspondence for Volume IV, 1926-1927 (Box 162, Folder 1)
    - Source Volumes - Orders and Correspondence for Volumes V, VI and VII, 1926-1927 (Box 162, Folder 2)
    - Source Volumes - Orders and Correspondence for Volumes VI and VII, 1927 (Box 162, Folder 3)
    - Source Volumes - Orders and Correspondence for Volume VII, 1927 (Box 162, Folder 4)
    - Source Volumes - Orders and Correspondence, 1925-1927 (Box 162, Folder 5)
    - Source Volumes - Orders and Correspondence, 1926-1927 (Box 163, Folder 1)
    - Source Volumes - Lists of Individuals interested in purchasing books, 1923, 1925 (See Oversize Box 165)
    - Speakers, 1919-1921 (Box 163, Folder 2)
    - Special Contributors, 1919, 1921-1922 and 1925 (Box 163, Folder 3)
    - State Service Records, 1919-1922 (Box 163, Folder 4)
    - Stearnes, R. C., Field Agent, 1920-1921 (Box 163, Folder 5)
    - Stockton, Bee, 1922-1923 and 1925-1926 (Box 163, Folder 6)
    - Supervisors, County Board of - Appropriations, 1920 (Box 163, Folder 7)
    - Supplement Number 1, 1921 (Box 163, Folder 8)
    - Supplement Number 2 and 3, 1921 (Box 163, Folder 9)
    - Supplement Number 4, 1921 (Box 164, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified (See Oversize Box 165)
    - Veteran's Bureau (See Oversize Box 165)
    - War and Navy Departments, 1922-1926 (Box 164, Folder 2)
    - Wilson, J. Scott, 1921 (Box 164, Folder 3)
  - Oversize - Subseries A: Correspondence, General
    - American Legion, 1922-1924 (Box 165, Folder 1)
    - Clippings, 1919, 1921, 1923-1927 (Box 165, Folder 2)
    - Local Branches, Partial Index to Correspondence by Locality (Box 165, Folder 3)
    - Press Releases/Publicity, 1919 (Box 165, Folder 4)
    - Questionnaires, Samples and Other States (Box 165, Folder 5)
    - Reports, Field Agent, 1921 (Box 165, Folder 6)
    - Reports, Monthly Progress, 1920 (Box 165, Folder 7)
    - Source Volumes - Lists of Individuals interested in purchasing books, 1923, 1925 (Box 165, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified (Box 165, Folder 9)